<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
<title>Overview</title>

<para>
<figure><title>High level interaction between many of the main COMP_hack components.</title>
<mediaobject><imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="static/project_overview.png"/>
</imageobject></mediaobject></figure>
The project contains many components, some of which are Internet facing. A <emphasis>Client</emphasis> who wishes to play the game will usually interact with the <emphasis>Web Server</emphasis>, <emphasis>Lobby Server</emphasis>, and <emphasis>Channel Server</emphasis> (in that order). A <emphasis>Game Master</emphasis>, <emphasis>Server Administrator</emphasis>, or <emphasis>Developer</emphasis> may also interact with the <emphasis>World Server</emphasis> and <emphasis>ChanMan Server</emphasis>, as well as place a <emphasis>Logger</emphasis> between their <emphasis>Game Client</emphasis> and a <emphasis>Channel Server</emphasis> to observe and debug. Each of these components will be discussed in greater detail.
</para>

<section>
<title>Updater</title>
<para>The <emphasis>Updater</emphasis> is a replacement for the original updater provided by <emphasis>CAVE</emphasis>. The new updater provides the following enhanced features:
<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>A time stamp check to allow for fast loading when there are no new updates.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Compression of the file listing (<emphasis>hashlist.dat</emphasis> file) for faster updates.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>An embedded web client to prevent caching of update files and mismatch errors.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>The ability to select more than one lobby server to connect to when starting the <emphasis>Game Client</emphasis>.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Browser</title>
<para>The <emphasis>Browser</emphasis> is used by the player and game masters to interact with the <emphasis>Web Server</emphasis> to create and manage account information and access the item store. The <emphasis>Browser</emphasis> is not a component of this project.</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>GM Console</title>
<para>The <emphasis>Game Master Console</emphasis></para>
</section>

</section>
