<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
<title>Login Server Configuration</title>
 
<para>As with any xml file, it should start with this line:</para>
<para><code>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;</code></para>
<para>All settings are enclosed between the <emphasis>&lt;config&gt;</emphasis>
and <emphasis>&lt;/config&gt;</emphasis> tags. The first section is for the
network connection.</para>
<section>
<title>Network Connection</title>
<para><programlisting>
<![CDATA[<connection>
  <address>any</address>
  <port>10666</port>
</connection>]]>
</programlisting></para>
<para>The <emphasis>&lt;address&gt;</emphasis> setting is the IP address to
listen for connections on. If <emphasis>any</emphasis> is used, the server will
listen on all network interfaces. Otherwise, a specific IP address should be
specified. If you only want to listen for local loopback connections,
<emphasis>localhost</emphasis> can be used.</para>
<para>The <emphasis>&lt;port&gt;</emphasis> setting is the network port the
server will listen on. The default port is <emphasis>10666</emphasis>; however,
you can change this if you wish.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Error Logging</title>
<para><programlisting>
<![CDATA[<log>
  <levels>
    <debug>true</debug>
    <info>true</info>
    <warning>true</warning>
    <error>true</error>
    <critical>true</critical>
  </levels>
  <path>/var/log/comp_hack/login.log</path>
</log>]]>
</programlisting></para>
<para>The log <emphasis>&lt;path&gt;</emphasis> determines where the log for
the server is saved. This path should point to an existing directory that the
login server can write to. The log will be overwritten each time the server is
started. At this time, there is no appending or log rotation feature.</para>
<para>The tags under <emphasis>&lt;levels&gt;</emphasis> determine which types
of messages will be written to the log. Valid values are <emphasis>true
</emphasis> or <emphasis>false</emphasis>.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Database Connection</title>
<para><programlisting>
<![CDATA[<database>
  <driver>mysql</driver>
  <host>localhost</host>
  <username>root</username>
  <password>hackme</password>
  <database>comp_hack</database>
</database>]]>
</programlisting></para>
<para>The <emphasis>&lt;database&gt;</emphasis> section is used for accounts,
post item data, the list of characters for an account, and a few other items.
This information can be shared with the website. There are two types of
database you may use: <emphasis>MySQL</emphasis> and <emphasis>SQLite
</emphasis>.</para>
<para>The <emphasis>&lt;driver&gt;</emphasis> section determines if the
database engine is <emphasis>mysql</emphasis> or <emphasis>sqlite</emphasis>.
</para>
<para>The <emphasis>&lt;host&gt;</emphasis> section is the hostname or IP
address to use when connecting to the database. This option is only used for
<emphasis>MySQL</emphasis> databases.</para>
<para>The <emphasis>&lt;username&gt;</emphasis> and <emphasis>&lt;password&gt;
</emphasis> sections are used for authentication when connecting to the
database. This option is only used for <emphasis>MySQL</emphasis> databases.
</para>
<para>The <emphasis>&lt;database&gt;</emphasis> section contains the name of
the <emphasis>MySQL</emphasis> database or the path to the <emphasis>SQLite
</emphasis> database file. If the <emphasis>SQLite</emphasis> database does not
exist, the server will attempt to generate a default database when you first
run the server.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Web Authentication</title>
<para><programlisting>
<![CDATA[<webauth>
  <usessl>true</usessl>
  <pem>/etc/comp_hack/ssl/comp_hack.crt</pem>
  <cert>/etc/comp_hack/ssl/comp_hack.crt</cert>
  <ca>/etc/comp_hack/ssl/ca.crt</ca>
  <address>any</address>
  <port>10999</port>
</webauth>]]>
</programlisting></para>
<para>The <emphasis>&lt;webauth&gt;</emphasis> section is used for web
authentication in new versions of the client. New versions of the client use an
embedded Internet Explorer window to display a webpage for the login dialog.
After authenticating with the website, control is passed to the login server.
COMP_hack lobby has a built in web server for authentication.</para>
<para>The <emphasis>&lt;usessl&gt;</emphasis> section determines if SSL (https)
should be used for the connection. You should be using SSL encryption when
building a production server that others connect to. If you don’t use SSL
encryption, client passwords will be sent in plain text. Non-SSL authentication
should only be used for internal testing. The <emphasis>webaccess.sdat
</emphasis> file should point to the login server’s IP address and web
authentication port and use either http or https as appropriate. See the
updater documentation for more information on this file.</para>
<para>The <emphasis>&lt;pem&gt;</emphasis>, <emphasis>&lt;cert&gt;</emphasis>,
and <emphasis>&lt;ca&gt;</emphasis> files are used for SSL encryption and
should be provided by your SSL certificate authority.</para>
<para>The <emphasis>&lt;address&gt;</emphasis> and <emphasis>&lt;port&gt;
</emphasis> sections work just like their matching sections under
<emphasis>&lt;connection&gt;</emphasis> except they apply to the web
authentication component of the server.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Internal Server Connection</title>
<para><programlisting>
<![CDATA[<internal>
  <address>any</address>
  <port>48896</port>
  <key>hackme</key>
</internal>]]>
</programlisting></para>
<para>The <emphasis>&lt;address&gt;</emphasis> and <emphasis>&lt;port&gt;
</emphasis> sections work just like their matching sections under
<emphasis>&lt;connection&gt;</emphasis> except they apply to the internal
network component. The internal connection is used to communicate information
between the login server and all related channels.</para>
<para>The <emphasis>&lt;key&gt;</emphasis> section is used to authenticate the
channel connections. It should be a sufficiently long and random value. Please
note that internal connections should only happen on a local connection (either
a LAN connection between the servers or the loopback interface) to ensure added
security.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Client Versions</title>
<para><programlisting>
<![CDATA[<versions higher="true">
  <us>1624</us>
  <jp>1410</jp>
</versions>]]>
</programlisting></para>
<para>The versions section defines the client version required to connect to
the server. If the <emphasis>higher</emphasis> attribute is set to true, a
higher version number then the one listed will be allowed. This is useful if
you do not wish to change this value often or only care about a minimum
version. The <emphasis>&lt;us&gt;</emphasis> version is for any client that
has a version ending in “U” like “1.624U”. The <emphasis>&lt;jp&gt;</emphasis>
version is used for any other client.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Binary Data</title>
<para><programlisting>
<![CDATA[<data lang="ja">C:\Program Files\COMP_hack\BinaryData</data>]]>
</programlisting></para>
<para>The <emphasis>&lt;data&gt;</emphasis> section is used for game data
shared between the client and the server (like item data, zone data, etc.) and
should point to the <emphasis>BinaryData</emphasis> directory of the client
files. The <emphasis>lang</emphasis> attribute should be set to
<emphasis>ja</emphasis> if the BinaryData is from a Japanese client.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Playable Character Data</title>
<para><programlisting>
<![CDATA[<pcdata>/var/lib/comp_hack</pcdata>]]>
</programlisting></para>
<para>The <emphasis>&lt;pcdata&gt;</emphasis> section stores all playable
character data. This is where the majority of account and server data is
stored. This path should be writable by the server.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Worlds</title>
<para><programlisting>
<![CDATA[<worlds>
  <world id="0" userLevel="0">COMP_hack</world>
  <world id="1" userLevel="100">Test World</world>
</worlds>]]>
</programlisting></para>
<para>The <emphasis>&lt;worlds&gt;</emphasis> section is used to display the
list of worlds new characters can be created on. Each <emphasis>&lt;world&gt;
</emphasis> section contains the name of the world and should have a unique
<emphasis>id</emphasis> attribute. IDs should start at 0 and increment by one.
Do not have gaps in the IDs. It is recommended you list worlds in ID order to
prevent bugs. If the <emphasis>userLevel</emphasis> attribute is set, only
accounts that have a user level at or above this value can see and connect to
that world. GM accounts default to a user level of 1000 and normal accounts
have a user level of 0.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Ticket Cost</title>
<para><programlisting>
<![CDATA[<ticketCost>0</ticketCost>]]>
</programlisting></para>
<para>The <emphasis>&lt;ticketCost&gt;</emphasis> section defines how much cash
shop currency is required to purchase an additional character ticket. If the
account has no characters they will still be able to create a new characters
regardless of how many tickets they have purchased.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Character Deletion</title>
<para><programlisting>
<![CDATA[<deathTime>1440</deathTime>]]>
</programlisting></para>
<para>The <emphasis>&lt;deathTime&gt;</emphasis> section is how many minutes
it takes for a character marked for deletion to actually be removed from an
account.</para>
</section>

</section>
