<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
<title>Hacker's Guide</title>

<para>This chapter describes how the code is architected. The hope is that it will enable you to maintain, contribute to, or make small modifications to the project.</para>

<section>
<title>Code Branches and Tags</title>

<para>The code is split into two main branches: <emphasis>master</emphasis> and <emphasis>develop</emphasis>. Any work on the next release of the project is done in <emphasis>develop</emphasis>. When a release is complete it is merged into <emphasis>master</emphasis>. The <emphasis>master</emphasis> branch will always point to the latest stable version of the code. In addition to these two branches there is a special <emphasis>coverity_scan</emphasis> branch based off <emphasis>develop</emphasis> that is used for static analysis. All other branches correspond to the code name for a major release (<emphasis>pixie</emphasis>, <emphasis>lilim</emphasis>, <emphasis>kodama</emphasis>, etc). When working on updates for a service pack or hotfix the change should go into the branch for that major release. It should then be merged, cherry-picked or re-implemented in the <emphasis>develop</emphasis> branch for upcoming releases.</para>

<para>Each release of a major version, service pack or hotfix should have a tag. The tag should consist of the version number, code name, service pack (if any) and hotfix number (if any). The version number works as follows: MAJOR.MINOR.PATCH. In this case the major version is the numerical representation of the code name (1=pixie, 2=kodama, 3=lilim, etc). The minor version number is the service pack and the patch is the hotfix number. When making a pre-release the minor is usually set to 8 and the patch is set to 9. The minor would be incremented for a second release candidate. For example, lilim service pack 1 hotfix 2 would be <emphasis>3.1.2</emphasis>.</para>

</section><!-- Code Branches and Tags -->

<section>
<title>Build System</title>

<para>This project uses <ulink url="https://www.cmake.org">CMake</ulink> to generate the make files (on Linux) or project files (for Visual Studio) needed to build the server applications and utilities. Currently this is known working on Linux with make files or Ninja scripts as well as Visual Studio 2015. The software may be build-able with new versions of Visual Studio, Eclipse, Xcode or other platforms and build systems; however, these have not been tested yet and may require slight modifications. It is known to build with the GCC, Clang and MSVC compilers.</para>

<section>
<title>Dependencies</title>

<para>Dependencies are handled automatically by the CMake build scripts. There is four ways you can handle this:</para>
<para><orderedlist>
    <listitem><para>Extract pre-built binaries into a <emphasis>binaries</emphasis> directory in the root folder for the project.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Place zip files of the dependency source code in the <emphasis>deps</emphasis> directory in the root folder for the project.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Let the CMake scripts download the source zip files from GitHub.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Let the CMake scripts download the source from the GitHub repositories. To do this you must set <code>-DGIT_DEPENDENCIES=ON</code> when generating the build scripts.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist></para>

<para>Except in the case of pre-built binaries, the CMake script will build the external projects and then import the libraries into the build environment. The imported libraries should include the interface include directories needed to use in a project that links to them. For details on how these are built and where to add a new dependency, see <emphasis>cmake/external.cmake</emphasis> as well as <emphasis>cmake/binaries.cmake</emphasis>. When building the Debian package the source code needs to be included for the build to succeed (especially if building for a PPA). When adding a dependency be sure to update the <emphasis>contrib/sources.sh</emphasis> script to download the new dependency for these packages.</para>

<para>Dependencies are built static with the same build configuration as the main project. For MSVC you may use the static runtime as well by setting -DUSE_STATIC_RUNTIME=ON when generating the build scripts.</para>

<para>There is two dependencies that are not built external. One is <emphasis>sqlite</emphasis> which is included as a single file in the <emphasis>deps/sqlite3</emphasis> directory. The other is <emphasis>sqrat</emphasis> which consists of a series of template based headers. The <emphasis>sqrat</emphasis> dependency can fluctuate quite a bit so it was included as a submodule in the <emphasis>deps/sqrat</emphasis> directory. Be sure to initialize and update this submodule.</para>

</section><!-- Dependencies -->

<section>
<title>Automated Builds</title>

<para>The project is setup to create automated builds for Linux and Windows using <ulink url="https://travis-ci.org">Travis CI</ulink> and <ulink url="https://www.appveyor.com">AppVeyor</ulink> respectively. The scripts used to build the project in these environments can be found in the root directory of the project as <emphasis>.travis.yml</emphasis> and <emphasis>.appveyor.yml</emphasis> respectively. These builds are done in two to four stages: the external dependencies, objgen (optional), libobjects (optional) and the main project.</para>

<para>First, there is an <ulink url="https://github.com/comphack/external">external project repository</ulink> that is also built in the same way as the main project. This has a mirror copy of the <emphasis>cmake/external.cmake</emphasis> script. This will build and zip up the pre-compiled binaries. This is then added as a release for that <ulink url="https://github.com/comphack/external/releases">GitHub project</ulink>. The Windows build may need to be added manually. The scripts are then updated by a developer to point to the new release. Then the automated builds will run using these pre-built binaries to speed up the build process.</para>

<para>The <ulink url="https://github.com/comphack/objgen">objgen utility and library</ulink> can now be built as a separate project to speed up the automated builds. This is built and added to the main build in a similar fashion to the external project. It needs the external project just like the main build.</para>

<para>The <ulink url="https://github.com/comphack/libobjects">objects library</ulink> can now be built as a separate project to speed up the automated builds. This contains a copy of the object schema in libcomp. Both projects should be updated when this schema changes. This is built and added to the main build in a similar fashion to the external project. It needs the external project just like the main build. It also needs the objgen utility and library build mentioned above.</para>

<para>The automated builds may use Cotire for pre-compiled headers (PCH) and combine multiple small source files into a single file to speed up the build process. Usually the Linux GCC build on Travis CI is the most picky when it comes to warnings followed by Clang. The Visual Studio build emits warnings but does not error out when they are generated.</para>

<para>The Windows build on AppVeyor will generate the zip and msi releases as artifacts that you may download and test with. These are used during the release process as the clean build of the project.</para>

<para>Finally, if you merge code from <emphasis>develop</emphasis> into the <emphasis>coverity_scan</emphasis> branch it will run a static analysis of the code provided by <ulink url="https://scan.coverity.com/">Coverity</ulink>.</para>

</section><!-- Automated Builds -->

<section>
<title>Build Options</title>

<para>Here is a list of build options you may set when running CMake:</para>

<section>
<title>BUILD_DREAM</title>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Type:</emphasis> boolean</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Default:</emphasis> ON</para>
<para>This will build the dream and sandman sub-projects if they are cloned into the source tree as the directories <emphasis>dream</emphasis> and <emphasis>tools/sandman</emphasis> respectively.</para>
</section><!-- BUILD_DREAM -->

<section>
<title>GIT_DEPENDENCIES</title>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Type:</emphasis> boolean</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Default:</emphasis> OFF</para>
<para>This will download the external dependencies from the Git repositories instead of downloading a zip release. The branch for each external is specified in the <emphasis>cmake/external.cmake</emphasis> file.</para>
</section><!-- GIT_DEPENDENCIES -->

<section>
<title>SINGLE_SOURCE_PACKETS</title>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Type:</emphasis> boolean</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Default:</emphasis> OFF</para>
<para>This will combine all the packet parsing source files into a single source file for fast building. Enabling this option could cause issues depending on how the source was written; however, these issues are usually caught during the automated build.</para>
</section><!-- SINGLE_SOURCE_PACKETS -->

<section>
<title>SINGLE_OBJGEN</title>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Type:</emphasis> boolean</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Default:</emphasis> OFF</para>
<para>This will combine all the objgen generated source files into a single source file for fast building. This is currently not used because of circular dependencies on the template functions used to bind the objects into the scripting language (squirrel).</para>
</section><!-- SINGLE_OBJGEN -->

<section>
<title>USE_COTIRE</title>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Type:</emphasis> boolean</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Default:</emphasis> OFF</para>
<para>This will use Cotire to generate and build using a pre-compiled header (PCH). This is used by the automated builds to speed up the build process.</para>
</section><!-- USE_COTIRE -->

<section>
<title>NO_WARNINGS</title>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Type:</emphasis> boolean</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Default:</emphasis> OFF</para>
<para>This will disable the generation of errors when a warning is omitted. The warnings will still be shown but will not halt the build. This is handy when building on a new Linux system or for the Debian package (for the PPA). This should not be used during development or on the automated build system.</para>
</section><!-- NO_WARNINGS -->

<section>
<title>DISABLE_TESTING</title>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Type:</emphasis> boolean</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Default:</emphasis> OFF</para>
<para>This disables the build for the unit test applications.</para>
</section><!-- DISABLE_TESTING -->

<section>
<title>USE_STATIC_RUNTIME</title>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Type:</emphasis> boolean</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Default:</emphasis> OFF</para>
<para>This disables the build for the unit test applications.</para>
</section><!-- USE_STATIC_RUNTIME -->

<section>
<title>USE_PREBUILT_OBJECTS</title>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Type:</emphasis> boolean</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Default:</emphasis> OFF</para>
<para>This will use the pre-built objgen library and tools as well as a library of objects from libcomp to speed up the build process. This was added to prevent timeout of the automated builds.</para>
</section><!-- USE_PREBUILT_OBJECTS -->

<section>
<title>GENERATE_DOCUMENTATION</title>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Type:</emphasis> boolean</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Default:</emphasis> ON for Linux; OFF for Windows</para>
<para>This will enable or disable generation of the Doxygen API documentation and the Docbook guide you are reading now. If enabled, these only generate if the tools needed are found on the system.</para>
</section><!-- GENERATE_DOCUMENTATION -->

<section>
<title>WINDOWS_SERVICE</title>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Type:</emphasis> boolean</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Default:</emphasis> OFF</para>
<para>This will build the server applications as Windows services instead of a standalone application. This option is turned on for the AppVeyor build for official releases but may not be useful when developing.</para>
</section><!-- WINDOWS_SERVICE -->

<section>
<title>COVERALLS</title>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Type:</emphasis> boolean</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Default:</emphasis> OFF</para>
<para>This will generate code coverage to be uploaded to Coveralls. This is meant to be used on a Linux host.</para>
</section><!-- COVERALLS -->

<section>
<title>BUILD_OPTIMIZED</title>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Type:</emphasis> boolean</para>
<para><emphasis role="strong">Default:</emphasis> ON</para>
<para>This will built in release mode with aggressive optimizations. This should improve server performance but may not work for very very old systems. It may be useful to disable this when building for development for better debugging information.</para>
</section><!-- BUILD_OPTIMIZED -->

</section><!-- Build Options -->

</section><!-- Build System -->

<section>
<title>Architecture Overview</title>

<para>The project is split into three main servers: lobby, world and channel. Accounts are tied to a single lobby. This lobby can then connect to multiple worlds. Each world has characters bound to it that share the same depository and demon compendium. Each world has several channels connected to it that can manage different zones and dungeon instances in the world. There is one main database for accounts used by the lobby and one world database for each configured world. These may point to the same or a different database server. They should never re-use the same database data as this could violate the assumption that the lobby or each world has exclusive access to the database. This could cause odd bugs and data corruption.</para>

<para>In addition to the main server applications there is dream, libobjgen, libcomp, libtester, a test client, unit test suites and several utilities. The main library libcomp is linked to all the servers, dream, the test client and most of the tools. It provides any common code that is used by at least two of these applications.</para>

<para>The objgen utility (and the libobjgen library it uses for metadata) are used to generate C++ classes that wrap data structures. These are generated for libcomp and all 3 server applications. The generated classes can load and save to binary, XML and a SQL database. This works for loading both the binary data format used by the client and custom data files. The C++ classes can also bind to the scripting language (squirrel).</para>

<para>For an in-depth discussion of different aspects of the code it's recommended you look at the <ulink url="https://comphack.github.io">API documentation</ulink>. Most of what you need to know should be in there (or in this guide).</para>

</section><!-- Architecture Overview -->

<section>
<title>Object Generator (objgen)</title>

<para>The objgen utility takes XML files as input. These XML files describe the data structures that should be generated. What follows is the format of this XML and examples of how to use the generated code. All XML elements are enclosed in the following:</para>

<para><programlisting><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<objgen>
    <!-- Describe your objects here. -->
</objgen>
]]></programlisting></para>

<para>Each object described is converted to a C++ class. You may describe one as follows:</para>

<para><programlisting><![CDATA[
<object name="MyObject">
    <!-- Describe your member variables here. -->
</object>
]]></programlisting></para>

<para>The object has several properties that you can change:</para>

<para><itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">name</emphasis> - Name of the object. This is required.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">namespace</emphasis> - Namespace to place the object in (default is "objects")</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">scriptenabled</emphasis> - Enables generation of squirrel script bindings (default is false)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">location</emphasis> - Specifies the database ("lobby" or "world") the object is stored in (default is "lobby")</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">persistent</emphasis> - Enables generation of database load/save (default is true)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">baseobject</emphasis> - Name of the base class or object to inherit from (default is "" which uses libcomp::Object)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">inherited-construction</emphasis> - When set this will generated a method function called InheritedConstructon that takes the object name. This is used by the XML loading for a list of base objects. For example if you have a list of Action objects but you specify list elements as ActionSetNPCState or ActionAddRemoveStatus it will construct the proper action before storing in the list. (default is false)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>

<para>At a minimum each member variable has a type and a name:</para>

<para><programlisting><![CDATA[
<member type="u8" name="MyVariable"/>
]]></programlisting></para>

<para>Here is the list of valid types:</para>

<para><itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">bit, bool, flag</emphasis> - these are boolean types</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">u8</emphasis> - unsigned 8-bit integer</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">u16</emphasis> - unsigned 16-bit integer</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">u32</emphasis> - unsigned 32-bit integer</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">u64</emphasis> - unsigned 64-bit integer</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">s8</emphasis> - signed 8-bit integer</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">s16</emphasis> - signed 16-bit integer</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">s32</emphasis> - signed 32-bit integer</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">s64</emphasis> - signed 64-bit integer</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">f32, float, single</emphasis> - 32-bit single precision floating point</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">f64, double</emphasis> - 64-bit double precision floating point</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">enum</emphasis> - enumeration</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">string</emphasis> - a text string</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">ref, pref</emphasis> - reference to an object or persistent object (this isn't stored on disk / XML as that doesn't make sense)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>

<para>In addition to these types you may use the name of an object followed by * for a ref/pref to that specific object type.</para>

<para>Here is the common properties for all variables:</para>

<para><itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">caps</emphasis> - this will make the name appear in capital letters instead of camel case when generating the API. This is only useful if you variable names start with a lower-case letter.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">default</emphasis> - the default value for the member variable when the object is created (default depends on the type - usually blank, false or 0)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">inherited</emphasis> - This will not re-create the variable in a child class but can be used to override settings like a default value (default is false.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">key</emphasis> - generate a LoadXByKey function for this member variable</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">unique</emphasis> - generate a LoadXListByKey instead if this is false (default is true)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">padding</emphasis> - This will read or write the given number of zero bytes after the member function when loading and saving to a binary format (default is 0)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>

<para>Integer and floating point types has the following additional properties:</para>

<para><itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">min</emphasis> - Minimum value allowed (default is the min of the numeric type)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">max</emphasis> - Maximum value allowed (default is the max of the numeric type)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>

<para>A reference can have the following additional properties:</para>

<para><itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">nulldefault</emphasis> - The default value for the reference will be null instead of an empty default object (default is false)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>

<para>A string can have the following additional properties:</para>

<para><itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">empty</emphasis> - Allow an empty string as a valid value (default is true)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">regex</emphasis> - Regular expression the string must match or blank for none (default is "")</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">round</emphasis> - Round the length of the string to 2 or 4 bytes, padding it with zeroes (default is 0)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">lensz</emphasis> - Size in bytes of the length integer when saving to binary for a dynamic sized string. Can be 1, 2, or 4 (default is 4).</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">length</emphasis> - Size in bytes of a fixed length string. Can't be used with lensz or round (default is 0).</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">encoding</emphasis> - Storage encoding of the string (it's always UTF-8 in memory). Can be utf8, cp932, or cp1252 (default is utf8)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>

<para>An enum can have the following additional properties:</para>

<para><itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">underlying</emphasis> - integer type that is used to store the enumeration</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>

<para>An array must specify the number of elements allowed with the "size" property. Here is an example:</para>

<para><programlisting><![CDATA[
<member type="array" name="EquippedItems" size="15">
    <element type="Item*"/>
</member>
]]></programlisting></para>

<para>Here is an example of a list (dynamic array):</para>

<para><programlisting><![CDATA[
<member type="list" name="StatusEffects">
    <element type="StatusEffect*"/>
</member>
]]></programlisting></para>

<para>Here is an example of a set (a set is a list that has unique elements):</para>

<para><programlisting><![CDATA[
<member type="set" name="LearnedSkills">
    <element type="u32"/>
</member>
]]></programlisting></para>

<para>Here is an example of a map (associative array):</para>

<para><programlisting><![CDATA[
<member type="map" name="Materials">
    <key type="u32"/>
    <value type="u16"/>
</member>
]]></programlisting></para>

<para>Note that for a set or map you must use an integer or string type for the element or key type.</para>

<para>Objects are generated using the OBJGEN_XML CMake macro. This macro generates code using objgen. The arguments must start with the name of the output variable that will be passed to the ADD_EXECUTABLE command to ensure the generated files are compiled and linked to the application or library. The 2nd argument must be the main xml schema file that includes all other schema files and structures that code will be generated for. The remaining arguments will change depending on the extension (or lack of one). Files with the xml extension will be used as dependencies to the master xml schema. These are xml schema files that have been declared in an <code>&lt;include></code> element. Files that end in cpp or h are source files that will be generated. Only the source files defined will be generated despite what structures may be included in the xml schema. Finally, all other arguments are assumed to be a search path for other xml schema files that have be listed in an <code>&lt;include></code> element.</para>

<para>You can instead run the command on you own:</para>

<para><programlisting><![CDATA[
comp_objgen -I dir1 -I dir2 -o somefile.h -o somefile.cpp schema.xml moreschema.xml
]]></programlisting></para>

<para>Here <code>-I</code> is an include directory for XML schema and <code>-o</code> specifies an output file. You can specify multiple include directories, output files and XML schema files on a single command line.</para>

</section><!-- Object Generator (objgen) -->

<section>
<title>Release Process</title>

<para>The following section describes the process to go through for making a new release.</para>

<section>
<title>Clean Project</title>

<para>Go through the project and do the following:</para>

<para><itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Make sure any issues tagged for this release are resolved or moved to another milestone.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Ensure the latest build passed.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Run any applicable test suites on the latest build and make sure it passes.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Clean up the <ulink url="https://github.com/comphack/comp_hack/projects/1">Server Releases</ulink> project on GitHub.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Ensure the milestone has no open issues and close it.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>

</section><!-- Clean Project -->

<section>
<title>Patch Notes</title>

<para>Go through the commits and compile a list of what has changed (new features, bug fixes, etc). This list will need to be added into the Debian package (<emphasis>debian/changelog</emphasis> file, release entry on GitHUb and the Discord announcement).</para>

</section><!-- Patch Notes -->

<section>
<title>Update Documentation</title>

<para>The Doxygen generated API documentation should be downloaded from the AppVeyor release. The guide should be generated local on a Linux machine. Once all the documentation is generated, clone the <ulink url="https://github.com/comphack/comphack.github.io">comphack.github.io</ulink> repository. Remove any existing documentation files and add in the new files for a new commit. This should update the website.</para>

</section><!-- Update Documentation -->

<section>
<title>Update Version Information</title>

<para>Go into the top of the main <emphasis>CMakeLists.txt</emphasis> and change the version to match the release about to be created.</para>

<para>Confirm that the <emphasis>contrib/sources.sh</emphasis> zip files match those listed in <emphasis>cmake/external.cmake</emphasis> or the Debian build may fail.</para>

<para>Create a new entry in the Debian package (<code>debchange -i</code>). Make sure to include the change log items. The format of this file is very picky. It would be good to do a local test build before pushing this to the PPA with this command:</para>

<para><programlisting>
dpkg-buildpackage -us -uc
</programlisting></para>

<para>When making the commit it's a good idea to describe the commit as the version intended as we are about to tag and branch it.</para>

</section><!-- Update Version Information -->

<section>
<title>Test Packages</title>

<para>Test both the Debian packages and the MSI produced by AppVeyor. If the version information is wrong or something is not working right, go fix it now.</para>

</section><!-- Test Packages -->

<section>
<title>Tag &amp; Release</title>

<para>Go onto GitHub and create a new pre-release. This will create a new tag. Please use the format from previous releases. This should be "v" followed by the version with a dash and then the release name. If this is a service pack or hotfix add another dash and the appropriate information (for example "-sp1" or "-hotfix1"). Title the release as shown in previous releases and include the change log. <emphasis role="strong">Make sure the release points to the right branch and commit.</emphasis>. It's especially important that the tag and branch are correct if last minute changes are made and the release is re-created multiple times.</para>

<para>After they pass, download the tagged version of the AppVeyor build. Rename to match (if wrong) before uploading to the release. Include the Windows zip and msi builds. The documentation build can be included too but is not required.</para>

<para>Tag the datastore repository to match.</para>

<para>After the PPA is updated as well, download and test the release build. Once it looks OK set it to an official release.</para>

</section><!-- Tag & Release -->

<section>
<title>Update PPA</title>

<para>Update the PPA with the new Debian build. Clone the correct version of the code, download the source to the dependencies and remove the git history. Upload to the PPA and ensure the build completes and the packages are published. Test the published packages and make fixes as needed. Here is an example flow (you may need to change some things):</para>

<para><programlisting>
git clone -b v3.1.0-lilim-sp1 git@github.com:comphack/comp_hack.git
cd comp_hack/
git submodule update --init
rm -rf .git
contrib/sources.sh
debuild -S -sa
cd ..
dput ppa:compomega/comphack *.changes
</programlisting></para>

</section><!-- Update PPA -->

<section>
<title>Create Branch</title>

<para>First, merge the <emphasis>develop</emphasis> branch into <emphasis>master</emphasis>. This should be a clean fast-forward. If this is a major release, create the appropriately named branch off of <emphasis>develop</emphasis>. Bug fixes and other changes for a service pack or hot fixes should go into this branch from now on.</para>

<para>Go to the <emphasis>develop</emphasis> branch and change the version back to unstable with a new commit. This way nobody forgets to change it and makes test builds as a release!</para>

</section><!-- Create Branch -->

<section>
<title>Announce Release</title>

<para>Announce the release on Discord and wherever else is appropriate. Be sure to include the change log of cool new features to get everyone excited. Party hard.</para>

</section><!-- Announce Release -->

</section><!-- Release Process -->

</chapter>
